National Ballet 034
People's Archive, MLK Library
National Ballet Records
1962-1974
People's Archive, MLK Library
National Ballet (Washington, D.C.) (1962-1974)
034
50 Linear feet
91 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Trustee Minutes, 1964-1974 Contains minutes of the Board of Trustees of the National Ballet. Series 2: Ballets Performed, 1962-1974 Contains primarily photographs from performances of the National Ballet as well as a few programs. The folders are arranged alphabetically by the title of the performance. The series also contains a chronology of the National Ballet Repertory from 1962-1967 prepared by Debra Devoe, which appears at the end of the series. Series 3: Biographical Files, 1972-1974 Folders in the series contain files on certain dancers who performed with the National Ballet. The folders are arranged alphabetically by the surname of the performer. Press biographies, critics quotes, and advance sheets appear at the end of the series. Series 4: Programs and Promotional Material, 1963-1972 This series contains primarily programs, flyers, and other promotional materials for productions of the National Ballet. The materials are arranged chronologically by date of the performance. Series 5: Traveling Performances, 1973-1974 This series includes correspondence, contracts, internal memoranda, stage information questionnaires, rehearsal and performance schedules, technical information sheets, reviews, and clippings regarding traveling performances of the Ballet. Handwritten log books maintained on the road record schedules, staging requirements, and other notes on the performances; and appear first with the remainder of the materials arranged alphabetically by the title of the performance. Series 6: Publicity, 1963-1975 This series contains press releases, editions of Ballerina: the National Ballet News, subscription flyers, and clippings. A book containing clippings of advertisements for National Ballet performances is also contained in the series. Series 7: Stage Direction, ca. 1962-1974 Handwritten stage directions for each play as well as some musical scores are contained in this series. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title of the ballet. Series 8: Audiovisual Materials, ca. 1964-1974 This series contains audiotapes, a videotape, microfilm of musical scores, and photographs. The materials are further arranged into subseries by format. Subseries 1: Audio and Video Recordings, ca. 1964-1974 Contains 93 reel-to-reel audiotapes of ballets performed by the National Ballet. The series also contains a video film of a February 1973 performance on WTTG television by the company and tapes of interviews with members of the company, including Frederick Franklin and Ralph Black. The tapes are loosely arranged alphabetically by title with interviews and duplicates in other formats at the end. Subseries 2: Microfilm, ca. 1971 Contains microfilm of selected scores from ballets performed by the company. The microfilm containers are loosely arranged by title of the ballet. Subseries 3: Photographs, ca. 1970s Contains snapshots, proofsheets, a photo album commemorating the first 4 years of the company, and other photographs from rehearsals, performances, and the academic school of the National Ballet. Series 9: Administration, 1966-1974 This series contains a small amount of records regarding the finances, history, and general administration of the company. Items include a history of the National Ballet, sample form letters, press books, Kennedy Center information, brochures worksheet, New York publicity, and printed material of the Ballet. Series 10: Stage Design, ca. 1962-1974 This series contains hanging plots, board studies, and set designs for selected performances of the National Ballet. The materials are loosely arranged alphabetically by title of the ballet. Series 11: Musical Scores, ca. 1962-1974 This series contains marked scores of music for ballets performed by the National Ballet. The scores are arranged alphabetically by title of the ballet. Series 12: Scrapbooks, 1940, 1962-1974 Includes scrapbooks of clippings, programs, invitations, press releases, and other memorabilia compiled to document the company's activities from 1962 through 1974. The series also contains two scrapbooks of clippings of magazine and newspaper articles from the 1940s about composers and conductors of the period such as Toscanini, Shostakovich, and Rachmaninoff.
Biographical / Historical
The National Ballet was founded as the resident ballet company of Washington, D.C. in 1962 by Jean Riddell. Frederick Franklin was the artistic director and was joined by Ben Stevenson in 1971. The Ballet gave its first performance on January 3, 1963 at Lisner Auditorium. During its 12 years, the company also performed at the Kennedy Center and in 275 cities throughout North America. In 1974 the Company disbanded due to financial problems.
Custodial History
Jean Riddell donated the records to the Library in 1976.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of trustee minutes, programs, advertisements, press releases, clippings, biographical files, promotional materials, and scrapbooks regarding the promotion and administration of the National Ballet. The collection also contains musical scores, hanging plots, stage directions, board studies, set designs, videotapes, audiotapes, microforms, and photographs which document its artistic work. The records are arranged into 12 series.
Arts; Music; Performing Arts; Ballet; National Ballet (Washington, D.C.); Scrapbooks; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc); Organizational Records; Advertising
- Series 1: Trustee Minutes, 1964-1974
  Scope and Contents
  Contains minutes of the Board of Trustees of the National Ballet.
  - Minutes, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Ballets Performed, 1962-1974
  Contains primarily photographs from performances of the National Ballet as well as a few programs. The folders are arranged alphabetically by title of the performance. The series also contains a chronology of the National Ballet Repertory from 1962-1967 prepared by Debra Devoe, which appears at the end of the series.
  - Bachianas, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bartok Concerto, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cinderella, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Black Swan, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "The Catalyst", Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cinderella, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cinderella, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Combat, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Con Amore, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Concerto Baroceo, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Coppelia, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Le Corsaire, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Don Quixote, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Early Voyagers, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Eaters of Darkness, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Four Temperaments, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Giselle, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Graduation Ball, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Harlequinade, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Homage, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Jeu de Cartes, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Jungle, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Midsummer Nights Dream, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Night, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Nutcracker, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Nutcracker, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Out of Darkness, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Paquita, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Paquita, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Pas de Quatre, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Peter and the Wolf, Undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Prodigal Son, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Rhythm 3, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Seranade, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Serenade, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Sleeping Beauty, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Sleeping Beauty, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - La Sonnambula, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Swan Lake, Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Swan Lake, Undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Les Sylphides, Undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Les Sylphides, Undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Three Preludes, Undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Tribute, Undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Through the Edge, Undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Variations for Four, Undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Water Study, Undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Witch Boy, Undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Chronology of National Ballet repertory by Debra Devoe, 1962-1967 (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Series 3: Biographical Files, 1972-1974
  Folders in the series contain files on certain dancers who performed with the National Ballet. The folders are arranged alphabetically first by name of the performer. Biographies and critics quotes for use by the press for certain performers as well as advance sheets appear at the end of the series.
  - Leslie Adres - Marilyn Burr, Undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Marilyn Burr - Joanne Danto, Undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Ottavio Derosa (conductor) - Peter Farmer, Undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Dame Margot Fonteyn, Undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Frederic Franklin (co-artistic director) - Edward Haynes, Undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Paul Higginbotham - Desmond Kelly, Undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Christina Knoblach (principal dancer) - Kevin McKenzie, 1972-1973 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Roni Mahler - Dennis Pool, Undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Andrea Price – Frederic Strobel, Undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Robert Troll – Elizabeth Wade, Undated (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Biographies and critics quotes for use by the press, Undated (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Biographies and critics quotes for use by the press, Undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Advance Sheets, Undated (Box 30, Folder 3)
- Series 4: Programs and Promotional Material, 1963-1972
  This series contains primarily programs, flyers, and other promotional materials for productions of the National Ballet. The materials are arranged chronologically by date of the performance.
  - Untitled, 1963-1968 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, November 1968-March 1969 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, April 1969-March 1970 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, October 1971-January 1972 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 26390 (Box 35, Folder 1)
- Series 5: Traveling Performances, 1973-1974
  This series includes correspondence, contracts, internal memoranda, stage information questionnaires, rehearsal and performance schedules, technical information sheets, reviews, and clippings regarding traveling performances of the Ballet. Performances took place in every region of the U.S. including such states as North Carolina, California, Alabama, New York, Texas, and Kansas. Handwritten log books maintained on the road to record schedules, staging requirements, and other notes on the performances appear first with the remainder of the materials arranged alphabetically by title of the performance.
  - Untitled, 1973-1974 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Akron, OH - Brooklyn College, Undated (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Carbondale, IL - Fredericksburg, VA, Undated (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Greensboro, NC - Lawrence, KS, Undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Lawton, OK - Mobile, AL, Undated (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Muncie, IN - Ocala, FL, Undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Olean, NY - Salisbury, MD, Undated (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - San Antonio, TX -Toledo, OH, Undated (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Torrence, CA -Yakima, WA, Undated (Box 44, Folder 1)
- Series 6: Publicity, 1963-1975
  This series contains press releases, editions of Ballerina: the National Ballet News, subscription flyers, and clippings regarding performances. A book containing clippings of advertisements for National Ballet performances is also contained in the series.
  - Advertising Book, 1963-1965 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Advertising Book, 1973-1975 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Ballerina: National Ballet News, Undated (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Subscription flyers, Undated (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Press releases, Undated (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, Undated (Box 46, Folder 4)
- Series 7: Stage Direction, ca. 1962-1974
  Handwritten stage directions for each play as well as some musical scores are contained in this series. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title of the ballet.
  - "Bachianas" to "Concerto in D Minor", Undated (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - "Creation" to "Legend of the Pearl", Undated (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - "Night" to "Swan Lake", Undated (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - "Tango-Chikane" to "Warm Up", Undated (Box 50, Folder 1)
- Series 8: Audiovisual Materials, ca. 1964-1974
  This series contains audiotapes, a videotape, microfilm of musical scores, and photographs. The materials are further arranged into subseries by format.
  - Subseries 1: Audio and Video Recordings, ca. 1964-1974
    Contains 93 reel-to-reel audiotapes of ballets performed by the National Ballet. The series also contains a video film of a February 1973 performance on WTTG television by the company and tapes of interviews with members of the company, including Frederick Franklin and Ralph Black. The tapes are loosely arranged alphabetically by title with interviews and duplicates in other formats at the end.
    - Con Amore, Undated (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Coppelia, Undated (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Barocco, Undated (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Cinderella, Undated (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Bachianas, Undated (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Bartok Piano Concerto No.3, Undated (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Conversations, Undated (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Catalyst, Undated (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Concerto Barocco, Undated (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Courante, Undated (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Creation of the World, Undated (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Dance Brillante, Undated (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Don Quixote, Undated (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Eaters, Undated (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Legend of the Pearl, Undated (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Giselle, Undated (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - Jeu de Cartes, Undated (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - Night, Undated (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Nutcracker, 1967 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Homage, Undated (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - Jungle, Undated (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - La Peri and Fanfare, Undated (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Prodigal Son, Undated (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Raymonda, Undated (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Seeds, Undated (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Serenade, Undated (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Sleeping Beauty, Undated (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - La Sonnambula, Undated (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Streetcar, Undated (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - Swan Lake, Undated (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - Les Sylphides, Undated (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - La Sommnabula, Undated (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Tango Chicane, Undated (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Tempraments, Undated (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - Tribute, 1971 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Variations for Four, 1964 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Warm Up, Undated (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Witch Boy, Undated (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Britton's Young Persons Guide to the Orchestra, Undated (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - Tapes of interviews and unidentified tapes, Undated (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - Paquita, Undated (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - Pas de Deux "Gayne", Undated (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - Pas de Quartre, Undated (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Interviews, Undated (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - WTTG video film tape, February 1973 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - "Night" 16 mm film, Undated (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Microfilm, ca. 1971
    Contains microfilm of selected scores from ballets performed by the company. The microfilm containers are loosely arranged by title of the ballet.
    - Bartok (2 containers), Undated (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Black Swan, Undated (Box 62, Folder 2)
    - Cinderella (5 containers), Undated (Box 62, Folder 3)
    - Combat, Undated (Box 62, Folder 4)
    - Copelia Con Amore Pas de Deux, Undated (Box 62, Folder 5)
    - Gayeneh, Undated (Box 62, Folder 6)
    - Othello, Undated (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Paquita and Raymonda (4 containers), Undated (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Paquita and Seeds (4 boxes), Undated (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - La Sylphide, Undated (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - Witch Boy (2 boxes), Undated (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified, Undated (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Photographs, ca. 1970s
    Contains snapshots, proofsheets, a photo album commemorating the first 4 years of the company, and other photographs from rehearsals, performances, and the academic school of the National Ballet.
    - 4 Ballerinas (Barr, Fulton, Lipinski, and Le Comte with Frederick Franklin), Undated (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - Photo album, Undated (Box 64, Folder 2)
    - Snapshots and proofsheets, Undated (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - Kennedy Center, Undated (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, snapshots, and proofsheets, Undated (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, snapshots, and proof sheets, Undated (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, snapshots, and proof sheets, Undated (Box 66, Folder 1)
- Series 9: Administration, 1966-1974
  This series contains a small amount of records regarding the finances, history, and general administration of the company. Items include a history of the National Ballet, sample form letters, press book, Kennedy Center information, brochures worksheet, New York publicity, and printed material of the Ballet.
  - Brochures, Undated (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Floor Plans, Undated (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - History of the Company, Undated (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Kennedy Center Info, Undated (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - Petty Cash Forms, Undated (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - Press book, Undated (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - Requests for Information, Undated (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Sample Form Letters, Undated (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - SM Q-sheets, Undated (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Stencils, Undated (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - Three Preludes, Undated (Box 68, Folder 6)
  - Travel Orders, Undated (Box 68, Folder 7)
  - Printed Materials, Undated (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - New York Publicity, Undated (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - Publicity Brochures, Undated (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - Light Plot Q Sheets, Undated (Box 69, Folder 4)
- Series 10: Stage Design, ca. 1962-1974
  This series contains hanging plots, board studies, and set designs for selected performances of the National Ballet. The materials are loosely arranged alphabetically by title of the ballet.
  - Hanging Plots and board studies for: Nutcracker, Graduation Ball, Concerto Baccaccio, Coppelia, Gisele, Homage, Les Sylphide, Prodigal Son, Swan Lake, Tango, and Witch Boy, Undated (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - Line plots, set design, etc. for Streetcar, Cinderella, Les Sylphide, Undated (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - Line plots, set design, etc. for Bartok Concerto, Blossom, Jacob's Pillow, Jungle, La Sonnambula, Les Sylphides, Meadow Brook, and Water Study, Undated (Box 72, Folder 1)
- Series 11: Musical Scores, ca. 1962-1974
  This series contains marked scores of music for ballets performed by the National Ballet. The scores are arranged alphabetically by title of the ballet.
  - Legend of the Pearl, Undated (Box 73, Folder 1)
  - Legend of the Pearl, Undated (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - Legend of the Pearl, Undated (Box 75, Folder 1)
  - Othello, Undated (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - Othello, Undated (Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Le Maure De Venise (Othello), Undated (Box 78, Folder 1)
  - Raymonda, Undated (Box 79, Folder 1)
  - Romeo and Juliet, Undated (Box 80, Folder 1)
  - A Streetcar Named Desire, Undated (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - Touch and Go (Dance Variation for Piano), Undated (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - Touch and Go (Dance Variation for Piano), Undated (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - Witchboy, Undated (Box 84, Folder 1)
  - Witchboy, Undated (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 87, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 88, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 89, Folder 1)
- Series 12: Scrapbooks, 1940, 1962-1974
  Includes scrapbooks of clippings, programs, invitations, press releases, and other memorabilia compiled to document the company's activities from 1962 through 1974. The series also contains two scrapbooks of clippings of magazine and newspaper articles from the 1940s about composers and conductors of the period such as Toscanini, Shostakovich, and Rachmaninoff.
  - Scrapbooks, 1940s (Box 91, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1940s (Box 91, Folder 2)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1962-1963 (Box 92, Folder 1)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1963-1964 (Box 92, Folder 2)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1964-1965 (Box 92, Folder 3)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1966-1967 (Box 92, Folder 4)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1967-1968 (Box 92, Folder 5)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1969-1970 (Box 92, Folder 6)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1969-1971 (Box 92, Folder 7)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1972 (Box 92, Folder 8)
  - Unboxed scrapbooks, 1973-1974 (Box 92, Folder 9)